<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>history on Shoals</title>
    <link>/tags/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in history on Shoals</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 16:28:36 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A day on Hadrian&#39;s Wall</title>
      <link>/posts/2022-05-07_hadrian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 16:28:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2022-05-07_hadrian/</guid>
      <description>Photo: Sycamore Gap
Greenhead I told everyone who asked that I slept well. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t really true; the room was well-heated and there&amp;rsquo;s nothing but a comforter, reinforcing the fact that I sleep best in the cold. On the flip side, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to complain because thanks to the over-powered heaters, every scrap of clothing and shoe I have is completely dry.
No rain is forecast for today, my third walking Hadrian&amp;rsquo;s Wall Path.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Otto and Eugene</title>
      <link>/posts/2021-01-10_otto-and-eugene/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 18:17:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2021-01-10_otto-and-eugene/</guid>
      <description>Officer Eugene Goodman receiving the Joint Meritorious Civilian Service Award, photo by Navy Petty Officer 1st Class Carlos M. Vazquez II
On November 9, 1938, Goebbels turned the SA loose on Jewish communities throughout Germany, in a pogrom now known as Kristallnacht. With the veneer of a &amp;ldquo;popular, spontaneous uprising&amp;rdquo;, nazis smashed Jewish business, attacked Jews, and arrested them in the thousands, heralding the horrors to come.
1400 Synagogues were burned or broken.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Family artifacts</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-03-09_chanel_number_5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 18:11:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-03-09_chanel_number_5/</guid>
      <description>My grandmother died last Spring.
We mourn of course, but she lived to 100, saw and did amazing things, and the family has more a sense of respectful awe than anything else. In any case this is actually about a bottle of her perfume that came to me recently.
Chanel #5.
My grandfather was the copilot on a B-24 heavy bomber in WWII, flying from East Anglia to the heart of the third reich.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
