<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    
    <title>Shoals</title>
    
    
    <description>A blog feed for Shoals</description>
    
    <link>/shoals</link>
    <atom:link href="/shoals/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Land ho!</title>
        <description>
          
          Mapbox is occasionally referred to - not uncharitably - as “The Tile Company”. It’s true; we deal with big amounts of data, and the most common map/reduce unit we use is the old standby Mercator/XYZ tile. My past and present colleagues have built some really cool tools to make these...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2023 09:04:44 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2023/08/17/land-tiles.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2023/08/17/land-tiles.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tradewinds</title>
        <description>
          
          Yesterday a friend asked for my help hauling his boat closer to shore, along Lake Champlain in the Northern part of town. The recent flooding elsewhere in Vermont had now reached the lake, and he was worried that the rising waters would carry off his summer recreation plans. So I...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 16:37:21 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2023/07/25/old-dock.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2023/07/25/old-dock.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A beautiful summer</title>
        <description>
          
          Summer is great. I keep forgetting this, but the shores of Lake Champlain - for a blessed few months every year - are an absolute paradise. As I biked with my son to his summer camp this morning, I saw it in full display: boats on the water, strolling couples,...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 13:56:21 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2023/07/12/beautiful-summer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2023/07/12/beautiful-summer.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Once a cyclist</title>
        <description>
          
          Oh check it out - another middle-aged man on a bike, clad in lycra, spouting opinions. sigh. Now that I’ve been forced to ditch running, I’ve started cycling. Late in a Vermont winter, this has meant ponying up for a trainer attachment, plugging my old cross bike into it, and...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 17:13:18 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2023/04/02/once-a-cyclist.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2023/04/02/once-a-cyclist.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A New Story</title>
        <description>
          
          It’s late winter. I still run in the dark, though I get traces of dawn now. Surfaces are ice, the wind blows viciously, and my miles get slower and slower. This is always a hard time of year to be a runner. This year it’s harder than ever. My right...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 16:01:04 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2023/03/10/a-new-story.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2023/03/10/a-new-story.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Migrating with tusks and a trunk</title>
        <description>
          
          Y’all. I’ve wandered over to Mastodon from Twitter, along with a goodly number of other folks from the broad geo-sphere, and it’s . . . nice. Feel easier to post random musings. Less motive, less image. But I rolled back over to Twitter right quick when I wanted to get...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 16:35:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2022/11/13/migrating.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2022/11/13/migrating.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adventures of a smartwatch in Paris [UPDATE: MYSTERY SOLVED]</title>
        <description>
          
          Follow along using this map made with Felt One day this past July, I got up early and started a long run around Paris. I’ve found this practice to be the easiest way to explore without being an insufferable tourist. As I usually do, I started tracking the run with...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 10:31:42 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2022/10/10/watch-in-paris.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2022/10/10/watch-in-paris.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A day on Hadrian&apos;s Wall</title>
        <description>
          
          Photo: Sycamore Gap Greenhead I told everyone who asked that I slept well. It wasn’t really true; the room was well-heated and there’s nothing but a comforter, reinforcing the fact that I sleep best in the cold. On the flip side, it’s impossible to complain because thanks to the over-powered...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 16:28:36 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2022/05/07/hadrian.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2022/05/07/hadrian.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The things he carried</title>
        <description>
          
          The time had finally come to sort through and [mostly] discard the stuff I’d accumulated in the last days when higher education was conducted on paper. What follows is merely a selection. Snowbowl trail map, 10/10 A seminal masterpiece of student ski cartography by the inimitable Dana Allen, lately of...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 19:42:22 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2022/03/09/grad-school-hoard.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2022/03/09/grad-school-hoard.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Compton</title>
        <description>
          
          Compton streetlights Generating points with PostGIS . . . to approximate streetlight locations in Compton, Los Angeles. Loose homage to Kendrick Lamar, strong shouts to Snoop, Dre, Mary J., and the map underneath the 2022 Superbowl Halftime Show, and big respect to the L.A. county streetlight spacing guidelines. Photo by...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 10:30:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2022/02/14/compton.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2022/02/14/compton.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to deploy a webpage in 2022</title>
        <description>
          
          Instructions for getting a [mostly] static website onto a custom domain, with https encryption, for [mostly] free. I’m finally writing this down after getting stuck on step 10 way too many times. Godspeed. Purchase the top-level domain - gandi.net is my current preferred registrar. Hopefully this will be the only...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 16:13:15 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2022/01/21/how-to-internet.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2022/01/21/how-to-internet.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2020 Census drop, yo.</title>
        <description>
          
          Photo via the National Archives: Fairlington, VA. A census enumerator getting data from a Virginia housewife for the 1950 Census. The 2020 numbers are in! Let’s take a look at the changes since 2010, Vermont-centric . . . Metros grew, but half of counties shrank (including 3 in VT, 👀...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 17:50:32 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2021/08/12/2020-census.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2021/08/12/2020-census.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Otto and Eugene</title>
        <description>
          
          Officer Eugene Goodman receiving the Joint Meritorious Civilian Service Award, photo by Navy Petty Officer 1st Class Carlos M. Vazquez II On November 9, 1938, Goebbels turned the SA loose on Jewish communities throughout Germany, in a pogrom now known as Kristallnacht. With the veneer of a “popular, spontaneous uprising”,...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 17:17:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2021/01/10/otto-and-eugene.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2021/01/10/otto-and-eugene.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deomocratizing data science where it counts</title>
        <description>
          
          We at Faraday are data science experts. We have a collective century of experience in the mystical arts of data whispering; we’ve transformed oceans of rows and columns, built and discarded thousands of databases, and molded far-seeing algorithms in a dozen programming languages. But we mostly use SQL. SQL is...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:48:15 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2020/07/14/sql.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2020/07/14/sql.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Family artifacts</title>
        <description>
          
          My grandmother died last Spring. We mourn of course, but she lived to 100, saw and did amazing things, and the family has more a sense of respectful awe than anything else. In any case this is actually about a bottle of her perfume that came to me recently. Chanel...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 18:11:09 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2020/03/09/chanel-number-5.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2020/03/09/chanel-number-5.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A full-throated defense of using Zipcodes for spatial analysis</title>
        <description>
          
          We, the data-folk of Faraday, agree wholeheartedly with our colleagues at Carto on this sensitive issue: In the USA, ZIP codes(™) are the worst-case scenario base unit for measuring geospatial relationships. Because: They’re widely-varying in size &amp;amp; shape They contain populations that range from 0 into the hundreds of thousands...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 16:16:07 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2019/08/28/zipcodes-for-spatial-analysis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2019/08/28/zipcodes-for-spatial-analysis.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Following a phone case</title>
        <description>
          
          The order is placed On CyberMonday I ordered one of those custom-printed phone case thingies because Google ran a hard sell. Can’t wait! Hmmm . . . looks like it shipped. Lemme check the status. Holy hell, it’s a map! It shows where my phone case is! Looks like it’s...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 19:13:11 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2018/11/19/a-journey.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2018/11/19/a-journey.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>All the Takes You’re About to See on the NYC-Snapchat Map Vandalism</title>
        <description>
          That’s right folks, it happened - an OpenStreetMap vandal made it to prime time: - 
          That’s right folks, it happened - an OpenStreetMap vandal made it to prime time: Anti-Semitic Vandalism Lists New York as &apos;Jewtropolis&apos; on Snapchat, CitiBike, and More About three weeks ago, some roblox-loving, likely-gamergater mini-nazi decided to re-label New York City in OSM (along with a bunch of other landmarks). It...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 13:37:23 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2018/08/30/all-the-takes-youre-about-to-see-on-the-nycsnapchat-map-vandalism.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2018/08/30/all-the-takes-youre-about-to-see-on-the-nycsnapchat-map-vandalism.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A true map</title>
        <description>
          Many an earnest cartographer/journalist/opinion-holder is currently debating — with varying degrees of condescension — the utility of the… - 
          Many an earnest cartographer/journalist/opinion-holder is currently debating — with varying degrees of condescension — the utility of the @nytimes’ latest map piece: While some arguments are specious (specifically, I’m not sure what species of monster you have to be to fail to enjoy a good birds-eye perspective), and others are just petty, the most...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 08:31:01 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2018/07/28/true-map.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2018/07/28/true-map.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bonten Poad: Generating fake Vermont placenames with a neural network</title>
        <description>
          Y’all, we’ve entered a computing epoch when AI is available to us at nearly the level of commodity entertainment. Take this experiment in… - 
          “Yup, take the Pendoil bridge just past Sad Cahue Village, and you’ll be up ta’ Ponkey before ya know it!” Y’all, we’ve entered a computing epoch when AI is available to us at nearly the level of commodity entertainment. Take this experiment in generative British placenames by Dan Hon; his...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2017 09:07:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/shoals/2017/07/20/bonten-poad-generating-fake-vermont-placenames-with-a-neural-network.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shoals/2017/07/20/bonten-poad-generating-fake-vermont-placenames-with-a-neural-network.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>