<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>data science on Shoals</title>
    <link>/tags/data-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in data science on Shoals</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:48:15 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deomocratizing data science where it counts</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-07-14_sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:48:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-07-14_sql/</guid>
      <description>We at Faraday are data science experts. We have a collective century of experience in the mystical arts of data whispering; we&amp;rsquo;ve transformed oceans of rows and columns, built and discarded thousands of databases, and molded far-seeing algorithms in a dozen programming languages.
But we mostly use SQL.
SQL is the old-as-the-hills workhorse that is interoperable with nearly everything, vaguely-consistent across ecosystems, and hella-flexible. We use it to count people over the age of 65, and we also use it to find local spatial autocorrelation across live-aggregated geographies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A full-throated defense of using Zipcodes for spatial analysis</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-08-28_zipcodes-for-spatial-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 16:16:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-08-28_zipcodes-for-spatial-analysis/</guid>
      <description>We, the data-folk of Faraday, agree wholeheartedly with our colleagues at Carto on this sensitive issue: In the USA, ZIP codes(™) are the worst-case scenario base unit for measuring geospatial relationships. Because:
They&amp;rsquo;re widely-varying in size &amp;amp; shape They contain populations that range from 0 into the hundreds of thousands They&amp;rsquo;re subject to mind-bogglingly-wide distributions in nearly every metric of human behavior (income, age, etc) The above post is exhaustive on these points.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
